{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this year, Roger Babson gave a speech predicting a \"terrific\" future disaster. The Pecora Commission investigated a disaster in this year. William Durant's display of confidence could not stop a disaster in this year described as the \"natural fruit of the orgy of speculation.\" This year's Black Tuesday featured millions of stock market shares traded in a panic. For 10 points, name this year in which the stock market crash began the Great Depression.",
      "answer": "1929 <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one poem by this man, a father warns his son of a time “when there is nothing in you / Except the Will which says to them ‘Hold on!’” The title character of another poem by this author is called a “squidgy-nosed old idol,” but “a better man than I am.” Another poem by this man exhorts “Send forth the best ye breed...to serve your captives’ need.” For 10 points, name this Indian-born English author of the poems “If--,” “Gunga Din,” and “The White Man’s Burden.”",
      "answer": "Rudyard Kipling <SH> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man joined John Stuart Skinner to negotiate the release of Dr. William Beanes. This man joined Colonel Skinner in boarding the HMS Tonnant for a prisoner exchange, but was prevented from returning to his own ship. The tune of \"To Anacreon in Heaven\" was used to accompany this man's poem about the bombardment of Fort McHenry. For 10 points, name this man who wrote about \"the rockets' red glare\" in \"The Star-Spangled Banner.\"",
      "answer": "Francis Scott Key <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "A teenager named Marcus Sarjeant shot at this person while she was riding her horse. In 1992, this woman's daughter, Anne, divorced Captain Mark Phillips, while her son, Andrew, separated from Sarah Ferguson. Harold Macmillan referred to her namesake by saying she had \"the heart and stomach of a man.\" She is married to Prince Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh. For 10 points, name this woman who became Queen of the United Kingdom in 1952.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth II <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, David Prosser Jr. defeated JoAnne Kloppenburg for a supreme court seat. Frustration with Act 10 led Tom Barrett to launch a second attempt to become this state's governor. In February 2011, all 14 Democrats in this state's State Senate inspired a similar tactic in Indiana by fleeing rather than vote on a bill they opposed. Before a failed 2012 recall here, its college dropout governor passed a bill weakening public-sector unions. For 10 points, name this state led by Scott Walker.",
      "answer": "Wisconsin <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler signed the Peace of Amasya with Tahmasp I, giving him control of Baghdad. This leader was known to his subjects as Kanuni or “Lawgiver”. He ordered the death of his oldest son Mustafa due to the influence of his wife Hürrem Sultan and executed grand vizier Ibrahim Pasha. His admiral Hayreddin Barbarossa won the Battle of Preveza and he defeated Louis II of Hungary at the Battle of Mohács (pr. MOE-hotch). For 10 points, name this longest reigning Ottoman sultan.",
      "answer": "Suleiman I <TR> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This party almost nominated Governor Benjamin Laney, who pulled out at the last minute before the convention. This party was formed after thirty five delegates walked out of another convention in response to a proposal by Hubert Humphrey. It nominated Fielding Wright for the Vice Presidency and declared they opposed \"the repeal of miscegenation statutes.\" For 10 points, name this pro-segregation party that nominated Strom Thurmond for the presidency in 1948.",
      "answer": "Dixiecrats <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city was the capital of a namesake Berber kingdom founded by Zawi ibn Ziri. A coup in this city featured the participation of Maryam, the wife of Yusuf I. Another ruler based in this city, Ibn al-Ahmar, took the name Muhammad I and founded the Nasrid dynasty before building this city’s Alhambra palace. This city was the last captured during the Reconquista. For 10 points, name this capital of a Muslim kingdom in southern Spain.",
      "answer": "Granada <SH> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 3"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This explorer named one island the “Island of Thieves” as its Chamorro people had no concept of ownership. This man’s main journey was chronicled by Antonio Pigafetta, and the slave Enrique helped him communicate with natives. He converted Rajah Humabon of Cebu to Christianity and passed Tierra del Fuego through a strait now named for him. For 10 points, name this Portuguese explorer who led the first expedition to circumnavigate the Earth.",
        "answer": "Ferdinand Magellan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Magellan sought the Maluku Islands in present day Indonesia, which were known to Europeans by what name?",
        "answer": "Spice Islands <TR> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A participant in this event who served as a \"boatswain\" was George Robert Twelves Hewes. This event began after a meeting at Faneuil (pr. FAN-yull) Hall that was soon moved to the Old South Meeting House and which denounced Governor Thomas Hutchinson's decision regarding the Dartmouth. Participants in it dressed as Mohawks. For 10 points, name this 1773 protest by the Sons of Liberty in which they threw shipments of a certain good into a Massachusetts harbor.",
        "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The tea destroyed in the Boston Tea Party was sent by what English joint-stock company that worked mostly in Asia?",
        "answer": "British East India Company <MC> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A substance discovered by William Huggins called “nebulium” turned out to be a doubly- ionized form of this substance. One macromolecule’s affinity for this substance is increased with increasing pH according to an effect discovered by Christian Bohr. One scientist discovered this substance by aiming sunlight at a mercury-containing compound, creating what he called “dephlogisticated air”. For 10 points, what substance discovered by Joseph Priestley is used in combustion reactions?",
        "answer": "O"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Danish chemist claimed to have discovered oxygen gas before Priestly, calling it “fire air”?",
        "answer": "Carl Wilhelm Scheele <EM> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this city during the 1990s, the Clean Hands investigation began by assessing the Tangentopoli bribery network. During the Tetrarchy, Maximian had his capital at this city while Diocletian ruled from Nicomedia. At the turn of the 16th century, a man nicknamed \"il Moro\" for his dark complexion commissioned Leonardo's The Last Supper as duke of this city. For 10 points, name this northern Italian city led by Lodovico Sforza, which was founded by the Celts under the name Mediolanum.",
        "answer": "Milano"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What family, whose crest showed a man getting swallowed by a sea monster, ruled Milan from the 13th through 15th centuries before the Sforza ascendancy?",
        "answer": "Visconti family <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1970’s, Hyman Rickover hypothesized this event was accidental. A fifty thousand dollar reward for information about the perpetrator of this event was published by William Randolph Hearst. This event caused the death of over two hundred sailors, afterwards forcing McKinley to ask Congress for a declaration of war. For 10 points, identify this 1898 event in Havana Harbor which resulted in the destruction of an American warship and the Spanish-American War.",
        "answer": "U.S.S. Maine explosion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The sinking of the Maine partially served as what necessary justification for the U.S. to declare war, a Latin term important in just war theory?",
        "answer": "casus belli <VP> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person used a basin dug by Nitokris to lower the water level of the Euphrates and defeat Nabonidus. Harpagus refused to kill this person as an infant. This person defeated an enemy by using a square formation and smelly camel corps at the Battle of Thymbra. This victor over Croesus (pr. crow-EE-sus) of the Lydian empire came to power by overthrowing his grandfather, the Mede Astyages (pr. ast-YAG-eez). For 10 points, name this founder of the Persian Empire.",
        "answer": "Cyrus the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cyrus the Great’s expanded Persian Empire was governed by men holding what title which existed under the Medes?",
        "answer": "Satraps <JZ> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man wrote about a clash of \"independent and dependent self-consciousness\" in a chapter often translated \"Lordship and Bondage\". This man claimed that Africa had not received the World Spirit yet in his Lectures on the Philosophy of History. \"Young\" followers of this man, who interpreted his views in terms of thesis, antithesis, and synthesis, included Karl Marx. For 10 points, name this German who discussed the dialectic in The Phenomenology of Spirit.",
        "answer": "Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Some critics of Hegel assume that he idealized what state, whose nobles were called junkers (pr. YOON-kurs), as a sort of \"end of history\"?",
        "answer": "Brandenburg-Prussia <MJ> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Before this campaign began, the neutral town of Khafji (pr. COFF-jee) was seized for a single day. This operation was the last that the USS Missouri fought in before its retirement, and it was declared to have lasted exactly 100 hours. \"Stormin’\" Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr. commanded coalition forces in this operation. For 10 points, name this UN operation led by the United States conducted against the Iraqi occupation of Kuwait.",
        "answer": "Operation Desert Storm"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What elite Iraqi force which fought in the First Gulf War wore maroon berets and reported directly to Saddam Hussein?",
        "answer": "Iraqi Republican Guard <VP> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 3"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE PACIFIC THEATER",
      "prompt": "Name the …",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country which fought the US in the Pacific Theater of World War Two.",
          "answer": "Empire of Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where four Japanese carriers were sunk, the turning point in the Pacific Theater",
          "answer": "Battle of Midway"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the Bataan Death march took place.",
          "answer": "Republic of the Philippines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for Japanese suicide pilots.",
          "answer": "Kamikaze pilots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Large Ryukyu island where the U.S. has kept bases since its 1945 wartime capture",
          "answer": "Okinawa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Plane which dropped “Fat Man” on Nagasaki",
          "answer": "Bockscar <JZ> {I}"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island chain containing Saipan and Tinian where a so-called “Turkey Shoot” took place.",
          "answer": "Marianas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Admiral nicknamed “Bull” who became the namesake of a Paul McCartney song",
          "answer": "William Halsey"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "NIKOLA TESLA",
      "prompt": "Name the nikola tesla...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Designed which type of electrical supply contrasted with direct current?",
          "answer": [
            "alternating current",
            "AC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Originally worked for which inventor based in Menlo Park?",
          "answer": "Thomas Alva Edison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was of this ethnicity, which names a present day country with capital Belgrade?",
          "answer": "Serbian"
        },
        {
          "question": "Worked with which type of radiation discovered by Wilhelm Röntgen?",
          "answer": "X-Rays"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used this technology to control a mechanical boat during an exhibition?",
          "answer": "radio control"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tried to create a “death ray” after seeing which type of spherical electrostatic generator?",
          "answer": "Van de Graaff Generator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Names the SI unit for which quantity?",
          "answer": "magnetic field"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was employed by which engineer whose namesake electric company later became CBS?",
          "answer": "George Westinghouse, Jr. <TR> {I}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE THIRD CRUSADE",
      "prompt": "Name the the third crusade...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "King known as “The Lionheart” who led the English crusaders?",
          "answer": "Richard I the Lionheart"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurdish unifier of Muslim forces and founder of the Ayyubid Dynasty?",
          "answer": "Saladin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Order that secured a crusader victory at Arsuf in 1191 and was founded by Hugues de Payens?",
          "answer": "Knights Templar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cause of death of Frederick Barbarossa en route to Jerusalem, after his horse slipped on rocks?",
          "answer": "drowning in the Saleph River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disastrous 1187 battle that preempted the crusade and took place between two peaks?",
          "answer": "Battle of Hattin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization that murdered Conrad of Montferrat and was led by the “elder of the mountain”?",
          "answer": "the Hashshashin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Poitevin (pr. PWAH-tuh-van) knight and second husband of Sybilla who claimed the throne of Jerusalem?",
          "answer": "Guy de Lusignan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crusader state led by Bohemond III throughout the crusade?",
          "answer": "Principality of Antioch <CKM> {I}"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This player was devastated after Dennis Johnson stole a ball from him in the final minute to end one NBA Finals. This man torched Robert Parish and Kevin McHale with what he called his \"junior sky-hook\" shot in a (20 pts)",
        "NBA Finals. A photo of this athlete at a Clippers game prompted Donald Sterling to complain about (10 pts)",
        "\"black people\" coming to the games. This man was the star player of a Michigan State team that won a title over frequent rival Larry Bird's team. For 10 points, name this Los Angeles Lakers point guard diagnosed with HIV in 1991."
      ],
      "answer": "Earvin “Magic” Johnson Jr. <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A wave of police attacks at a facility in this state were nicknamed the \"Battle of Bulls Run.\" A factory worker in this state, Geraldine Hoff, inspired the famous \"We Can Do It!\" poster. B-24s were produced by this state's (20 pts)",
        "Willow Run facility. This state's River Rouge Plant was depicted in a mural titled for its largest city's \"industry\" by Diego (10 pts)",
        "Rivera. That same plant was the site of the so-called Battle of the Overpass between security guards and members of the UAW. For 10 points, name this state home to the headquarters of the Ford Motor Company."
      ],
      "answer": "Michigan <KG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to the Letter of Aristeas, a leader of this place named Demetrios of Phaleron urged the creation of the Septuagint. While working in this place, Callimachus compiled the Pinakes. A smaller version of this place was located at the Temple of Serapeum, and this place was part of the (20 pts)",
        "Musaion. The items in this place were apocryphally said to either be useless or dangerous by Amr ibn al-As. Some theories about the (10 pts)",
        "destruction of this place claim that it was burned following a siege by Julius Caesar. For 10 points, name this repository of knowledge in ancient Alexandria."
      ],
      "answer": "the Library of Alexandria <JB> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The \"ring and girdle motif\" is carved into some of these objects. The Season 5 expedition revealed a buried underground component to many of these objects, whose largest examples include \"El Gigante\" and \"Paro.\" Much of the material for these artworks came from mining tuff from the Rano (20 pts)",
        "Raraku crater. A subset of these 887 objects displays topknots called pukao. Centuries before (10 pts)",
        "Chilean colonists arrived, these artworks were dragged into place on rolling logs by the Rapa Nui people. For 10 points, name these large stone statues found on a certain island in the Eastern Pacific Ocean."
      ],
      "answer": "moai <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 3"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) He’s not Hitler, but this leader unrealistically proposed tripling his country's agricultural output as part of his Four Year Plan. The phrase \"If we have rice, we will have absolutely everything\" ends a slogan from this man's reign, which sought to displace (20 pts)",
        "\"new people\" by evacuating city-dwellers into the countryside. This former schoolteacher, who studied in Paris during Norodom (10 pts)",
        "Sihanouk's reign, converted an old high school into Prison S-21, a complex which suppressed dissent in tandem with the \"killing fields.\" For 10 points, name this dictator who led the Khmer Rouge during the 1970s Cambodia."
      ],
      "answer": "Pol Pot <MJ>"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The group responsible for this action was led by Apis, who had earlier organized the murder of King Alexander Obrenović (pr. oh-BREN-oh-VITCH). The target of this event was selected after Muhamed Mehmedbašić (pr. meh-MED-bosh-ITCH) failed to kill Oskar Potiorek. One person involved was normally not allowed in ceremonial events due to her birth as a (20 pts)",
        "Bohemian aristocrat. The first attempt to perform this action failed when a bomb destroyed the wrong car near the Latin Bridge, but it was carried out successfully by a (10 pts)",
        "member of the Black Hand named Gavrilo Princip (pr. PRINTS-ip). For 10 points, which event in Sarajevo targeted the heir to the Austro-Hungarian throne and helped spark World War I?"
      ],
      "answer": "assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand <TR> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An advocate of this belief system was last seen on the isle of Comino after failing to convert Pope Nicholas III due to that pope's death by stroke. Abraham Abulafia advocated for this system, which was spurred on by the publications of the Castilian Moses de León. A system of assigning letters to numerical values called (20 pts)",
        "gematria, and \"emanations\" called sephirot, are important in this tradition's exegesis. Contemporary interest in this system led many (10 pts)",
        "Hollywood actors to wear a red thread, a trend with no basis in its primary text, the medieval Spanish Zohar. For 10 points, name this system of Jewish mysticism."
      ],
      "answer": "kabbalah <MJ> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Constitution, a newspaper published in this city by Henry Grady, declared the birth of an industrialized \"New South\" in the 1880s. The anti-Semitic People's Party Paper was published here by Tom Watson. Then-president Grover Cleveland presided over an 1895 (20 pts)",
        "exposition in this city where a speaker addressing cotton barons asked blacks to \"Cast down your (10 pts)",
        "bucket where you are.\" For 10 points, name this state capital where Booker T. Washington proposed a much-derided \"Compromise,\" which rebuilt along Peachtree Street after William Tecumseh Sherman burned it down in the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Atlanta, Georgia <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 3"
    }
  ]
}